Now do we know what to react actually is it's time to get our hands dirty.
imdi neye tepki vereceimizi biliyor muyuz ellerimizi kirletmenin zaman geldi.
And for that I was a code Penn Dot I O that is like our web editor which allows us to write very simple
Ve bunun iin Penn Dot O koduydu, bu, web editrmz gibi ok basit HVM LCS ve
HVM LCS and Javascript apps or really more like a playground.
Javascript uygulamalar veya daha ok oyun alan gibi yazmalarmz salyor.
We won't really use that to build real projects in this course.
Bunu, bu derste gerek projeler ina etmek iin kullanmayacaz.
We will use a local set up for that but it is great to dive into react so on codependent.
Bunun iin yerel bir kurulum kullanacaz, ancak baml olarak tepki vermek iin harekete gemek harika.
I know you can click on create and create a so-called pen that is simply a workspace where you can write
Oluturmay tklattnzdan ve yalnzca szck yazabileceiniz bir alma alan olan
h t m l c s s and Javascript code.
szde kalemi oluturabileceinizi biliyorum.
Now in this editor you've got three areas for H M L C S S and Javascript.
imdi bu editrde H M L C S S ve Javascript iin  alan var.
And now let's write a very simple application.
Ve imdi ok basit bir uygulama yazalm.
A demo to see how we write something with normal HVM all javascript and so on and how we then add react
Normal HVM ile tm javascript'lerle nasl bir eyler yazdmz grmek iin bir demo ve daha sonra bunun iin
to maybe have an easier time creating such an application for that.
byle bir uygulama oluturmann daha kolay bir zamanna sahip olduumuza tepki verdik.
And the HVM part of this editor ultrathin you death and you can quickly create this but typing Dev and
Ve bu editrn HVM ksm lm ok inceyor ve bunu hzl bir ekilde yaratabilirsin, ancak Dev
hitting tab.
yazp sekmeye basabilirsin.
This will automatically expand this.
Bu, bunu otomatik olarak geniletecektir.
And then there I will now add h one tech and some of the output.
Ve sonra imdi orada bir teknoloji ve baz kt ekleyeceim.
Max my name and below to the paragraph raise say your age 28.
Max ismim ve aada paragrafa ykseltmek 28 yan sylyor.
Does is my age.
Benim yamdaym.
And of course feel free to use your data here.
Ve elbette verilerinizi buradan kullanmaktan ekinmeyin.
So this now leads to the output below.
Dolaysyla bu imdi aadaki ktya gtrr.
It updates automatically.
Otomatik olarak gncellenir.
Now let's quickly give to some styling.
imdi biraz ekillendirmeye hzl bir ekilde balayalm.
Let's simply give Steve maybe a class of let's say person the name is up to you and add this person
Steve'e belki bir snf verelim diyelim ki kiinin ismi sana kalm ve bu kiiyi bu snf olarak grdmz gibi ekleyelim.
C as this class with some normal see is US code where I simply give this let's say a border.
Normal gryorsak US kodu burada sadece bunu syleyelim ki bu bir snr diyelim.
One pixel solid and does great with CCC and a box shadow of 0 2 pixels 2 pixels and lets say the same
piksel kat ve CCC ve kutu glgesi 0 2 piksel 2 piksel ile harika ve ayn gri diyelim.
gray.
Bir
Let's maybe lose us use a slightly brighter one here e.
Belki biraz daha parlak olan kullanmamz burada e kaybedelim e.
For the border.
Snr iin.
Let's not also give it as a width of let's say 200 pixels and the padding of 20 pixels and now we have
Diyelim ki 200 piksel ve 20 piksel dolgu diyelim genilii verelim ve imdi
this card like look you see below there.
aada grdnz gibi bu karta sahibiz.
Now that is such a person card information holding information about a person let's say.
imdi byle bir kii kart bilgi tutan bir kii hakknda bilgi edelim diyelim.
We can also said is to display in line block and give it a margin of 10 pixels because now what I can
blounda gsterilmesi ve ona 10 piksellik bir snr vermesi gerektiini de syleyebiliriz, nk imdi yapabileceim
do is I can of course replicate this and add a second person let's say Manue who has age of 29 that's
ey, bunu oaltabilir ve ikinci bir kiiyi ekleyebiliriz, meslektamz olan 29 yandaki Manue'y diyelim.
my colleague.
Ayrca izgi
So now we got these two person cards and you could easily think of this as normal web application where
imdi bu iki kiilik kartmz var ve bunu, normal web uygulamas olarak dnebilirsin; burada kullanclar hakknda
you output some information about users or about the team behind a tree or blog you're creating something
ya da byle bir ey yaratan bir aacn ya da blogun arkasndaki ekip hakknda
like that.
ktlar verebilirsin.
We're using only team Eliseus s here.
Eliseus takmn burada kullanyoruz.
Now we can already see one limitation kind of.
imdi bir eit snrlamay grebiliyoruz zaten.
We're always reusing the same HMO code here.
Hep ayn HMO kodunu burada tekrar kullanyoruz.
Now that isn't too problematic here.
imdi burada ok sorunlu deil.
It would be more problematic if we would do something with each of these snippets with javascript even
Bu snippet'lerin her birinde javascript ile bile bir eyler yaparsak daha fazla
but even without that we can think of this part here as a component.
sorunlu olurdu, ancak burada olmadan bu blm bir bileen olarak dnebiliriz.
Does person death always is structured in the same way just the data inside of it varies.
Kii lm daima ierisindeki veriler deitii gibi yaplandrlm mdr?
This is where re-act comes in though reactions to most as we connect is to javascript logic too.
Balantmza en ok tepki veren ey, yeniden hareketin geldii yerdir, bu da javascript mantna da uygundur.
But still we can already use react to create reusable components here.
Fakat yine de burada tekrar kullanlabilir bileenleri yaratmak iin tepki verebiliriz.
For that let's add react.
Bunun iin reaksiyona girelim.
I'm going to shrink this series as part a tiny bit and any javascript area.
Bu seriyi biraz kk ve herhangi bir javascript alan olarak kltmek iin gidiyorum.
First of all have to import react.
Her eyden nce tepki vermek zorundadr.
You can click on that your icon next to javascript and then you can download or import some external
Javascript'in yanndaki simgenizi tklatabilir ve ardndan baz harici javascript kitaplklarn indirebilir veya
javascript libraries and re-act is such an external library.
ie aktarabilir ve hareketi byle harici bir kitaplktr.
Actually it's so popular that Ancoats pen you can go to the quick and drop down and simply scroll to
Aslnda ok popler olan Ancoats kalemine hzlca gidebilir ve alr ve sadece tepki vermek
react.
zere ilerleyebilirsiniz.
And this will add it.
Ve bu onu ekleyecek.
Now here it adds version 15 Datsik start.
imdi burada srm 15 Datsik balatma ekliyor.
One might differ at the point of time you're viewing this in this course.
Biri bu derste grntlendiiniz anda farkl olabilir.
I will cover work in 16 so you are learning the latest react and then the local setup will use in this
reniyorsun ve daha sonra bu kursta kullanlacak yerel kurulumda son kullanacak olan en son tepki verecek.
course will also use dead latest react with.
Ben 16 almay kapsayacam, bylece en son tepki
No worries here however we're using an older one but for the demo here this does not matter at all.
Burada merak etmiyoruz, ancak eski bir tane kullanyoruz ancak demo iin burada bu hi nemli deil.
We also need to quick and react Dom.
Ayrca Dom'a abuk tepki gstermeliyiz.
That is another packet from the re-act team re-act itself kind of is the logic we need for creating
Bu, yeniden hareket ekibinin kendisinden baka bir paket de yeniden hareket tarzndaki bileenleri oluturmak
these re-act components.
iin ihtiya duyduumuz mantktr.
I told you that re-act is all about components re-act arm is then about rendering these components to
Sana syledim, yeniden harekete geme, bileenlerle ilgili tmyle re-act kol, gerekte bu bileenleri gerek Daun'a
the real Daun with these two packages added We're almost there.
sunma konusunda bu iki paketin eklenmesiyle ilgili Neredeyse oradayz.
But re-act use a special javascript syntax and a lot of next generation javascript features all come
size geri dnecektir. Burada, sizi reac kullanclarnn en nemli sonraki zelliklerine tanttm bir modl var.
back to this later in the course I'll have a whole module where I introduce you to the most important
Ancak yeniden hareket zel bir javascript szdizimi kullann ve bir sonraki jenerasyon javascript
next gen features reac users.
zelliklerinin birou daha sonra dersin ierisinde
So to unlock the usage of these features and the special syntax in the javascript preprocessor dropdown
Dolaysyla, bu zelliklerin kullanmn ve javascript nilemci alr mensndeki zel szdiziminin kilidini amak iin
you have to just babble.
sadece bastrmanz yeterlidir.
That's simply a tool which compiles the next generation javascript code you're writing here to code
Bu, burada yazdnz yeni jenerasyon javascript kodunu, istediimiz tm zelliklerle kod yazmak
that runs fine in the browser so that we write code with all features we want.
iin taraycda iyi alan koda derleyen bir aratr.
But ship code that works in the browser.
Ancak taraycda alan gemi kodu.
And with that you can click save and close and now we can start writing our re-act app here in the javascript
ve kapat' tklatabilirsin ve imdi yeniden eyleme geme uygulamamz javascript blmnde yazmaya balayabiliriz.
section.
Ve kaydet
So why don't we do that.
O halde neden bunu yapmiyoruz.
Let's create a re-act component so that we have a reusable custom HVM l element.
imdi yeniden kullanlabilir bir bileen oluturalm ki bylece yeniden kullanlabilir bir HVM l esi edineceiz.
We can use instead of repeating this HVM all code here on the left in its most basic form and you're
Bu HVM'nin tm kodlarn en basit formuyla solda tekrarlamak yerine kullanabilirsiniz ve bu dersin
going to learn about a different form in this course to its most basic form a re-act component is just
en temel biimine gre farkl bir form hakknda bilgi edineceksiniz. Tekrar eden bir bileen sadece
a function so we can't create a new function and maybe name this person.
bir ilevdir, bylece Yeni bir ilevi yaratmazsn ve belki de bu kiiyi adlandr.
Make sure it starts with a capital P is required to use it correctly with re-act this person component
Ba harfle balamasn salayn P, bu kiiyi yeniden yaplandrmak iin doru bir ekilde kullanmanz gerekir
is a normal function but it has to return decode.
ancak normal bir ilevdir ancak zm zmek zorundadr.
You actually want to render to the Dom and here re-act uses a special syntax which is called J as x.
Aslnda Dom'a sunmak istersiniz ve burada re-act, J olarak adlandrlan zel bir szdizimini kullanr x.
I'm using parentheses here to be able to write or to return some multi-line code.
Baz ok satrl kodu yazabilecek veya geri verebilmek iin parantez kullanyorum.
And now I'm going to copy the code here from the left and paste it into my return statement here.
Ve imdi kodu soldan kopyalayp burada iade ifademde yaptracam.
And this certainly looks strange No it looks like h tim l.
Ve bu kesinlikle garip grnyor No h tim l gibi grnyor.
In javascript which wouldn't work normally and it wouldn't if we hadn't added Batal here as a preprocessor
Normal almayacak olan javascript'te burada Batal' nilemci Balal olarak eklemediysek otomatik
Balal if configured correctly which it automatically is here allows us to use this special index which
olarak burada yaplandrlmsa, H. gibi grnen bu zel dizini
looks like H.T. mail but which isn't and I will dive deeper into that syntax in the next course modules.
kullanmamza izin vermez. T. posta deil ama deil ve bir sonraki ders modllerinde bu szdizimine derinlemesine dalacam.
It's called Deus Ex and it's just syntactical sugar.
Ad Deus Ex ve sadece szdizimsel eker.
Behind the scenes this gets compiled to normal Javascript code.
Sahnenin arkasnda bu normal Javascript kodu derlenir.
We can use it here though to have an easier time writing what we actually want to render.
Gerekten gstermek istediimiz eyi yazmak iin daha kolay bir zaman elde etmek iin burada kullanabilirsiniz.
Fine so now we got that function and I said the disease re-act component.
Gzel, imdi u fonksiyonu aldk ve hastaln yeniden hareket bileeni dedim.
But of course right now it's just a function to turn this into a re-act component.
Fakat tabii ki u an bunu sadece bir yeniden-eyleme bileen haline getirmek iin bir ilev.
We actually have to use react to render it to the screen.
Aslnda ekrana yanstmak iin tepki vermeliyiz.
So I'll get rid of my purse and you're on the left and instead are at a new div year and I'll give it
Bu yzden antamdan kurtulacam ve solda duruyorsun ve bunun yerine yeni bir div yldnmyse, sana
an idea of let's say p.
bir diyelim diye bir fikir vereceim.
You can choose any ID you want though.
stediiniz kimlii seebilirsiniz.
Now do you react package we imported is responsible for correctly parsing days code.
imdi ithal ettiimiz pakete, doru gn kodlarn ayrtrmakla sorumlu olduuna tepki veriyor musunuz?
Here is GSX code.
te GSX kodu.
The Obert package we imported was re-act dorm if you remember.
Hatrlarsan, ithal ettiimiz Obert paketi re-act yurt oldu.
You can always check your on the gear I can react on.
Her zaman tepki verebileceim vitese bakabilirsiniz.
This actually exposes an object re-act Dom written like that with Dom all being capital characters which
Bu aslnda, Dom nesnesinin render metoduna sahip byk karakterler olmas gibi, Dom nesnesinin re-act Dom
has a render method.
eklinde olduunu ortaya koymaktadr.
This method allows us to render a javascript function as a component to the real Dom and that treat
Bu yntem, gerek Dom'un bir bileeni olarak bir javascript ilevi oluturmamz ve onu Riak'n nemsedii eyin
it as a component part is exactly what Riak takes care about.
bir bileen paras olarak ele almamz salar.
We can then render this function but not by referencing it like this.
Daha sonra bu ilevi gerekletirebiliriz, ancak byle bir ileve bavurmadan yapabilirsiniz.
But by actually turning it into a HVM element again behind the scenes using this GSX syntax which is
Ancak aslnda tepki olarak anlalan bu GSX szdizimini kullanarak sahnelerin arkasnda tekrar bir
understood by react.
HVM esine dntrlyor.
So I write this as my custom self-closing HVM l element and render then takes another argument where
Bu yzden, bunu kendi kiisel kapan HVM l esi olarak yazyorum ve sonra render ilevi, burada iin nerede
I specify where to render this there.
olacan belirttiim baka bir argman ald.
I reach up to the document and it can use a query selector.
Belgeye ulayorum ve bir sorgu seici kullanabilirsiniz.
So normal javascript code to select any element with the ID P1 and that again is normal Javascript code.
Yani normal javascript kodu, P1 ile herhangi bir eyi semek ve bu yine normal Javascript kodudur.
The normal query selector.
Normal sorgu seici.
With that I'm telling re-act that I want to render this function a person component in displays here
Bununla tekrar hareket etmem gerektiini sylyorum, bu ilevi burada soldaki grntlerde bir kii bileeni haline
on the left and it does.
getirmek istiyorum ve yle.
Now the styling is lost because class actually is a key word in javascript so react touristas into class
imdi snf aslnda snf aslnda javascript anahtar kelimedir, nk turistik snf adna tepki ve bu
name and that's the best proof that this looks like H-G.
H-G gibi grnyor en iyi kantdr kaybolur.
But isn't.
Ama deil.
It uses a custom index which in 99 percent of the cases is like HGL But behind the scenes it's transformed
Durumlarn yzde 99'unda HGL'ye benzeyen zel bir dizin kullanyor Ama sahnelerin arkasnda ise
javascript.
javascript dntrlyor.
And now you see we have our person class here again Max treated as a custom component which we can all
gereini dorulayabilmemiz iin zel bir bileen olarak ele alnyor. blok ifadesi.
verify about the fact that our inline block stylin here is kind of ignored because we're wrapping this
Ve imdi grdnz gibi, Max, burada, Max, burada, bizim satr ii
in a custom element which is treated as a block statement.
blok stilinimizin bir tr grmezden geldii
Now I'll dive into styling in those cores.
imdi bu ekirdeklerde stile dalacam.
For now let's just be happy that we got our component rendered here.
imdilik, bileenimizi burada gsterdiimiz iin mutlu olalm.
It's not really reusable though.
Geri gerekten tekrar kullanlamaz.
If I had a second hook in my H.T. mouth fall here in my age you will part let's say with ITP too.
Eer benim ikinci bir kancam olsaydm T. azm burada benim yama geldiinde, ITP ile de syleyelim.
And I wanted to render a different component a different person.
Ve farkl bir bileeni farkl bir insan yapmak istedim.
I wouldn't have to hard code the values into that and actually create a new component.
Deerleri kodlamak zorundaym ve aslnda yeni bir bileen oluturmam gerekiyor.
The great thing about react and why components are so awesome and save us a lot of time is that we can
Yant vermenin ve bileenlerin o kadar mthi ve neden ok fazla zaman kazandnn en
configure them dynamically as we need them.
iyi yan, onlara ihtiyacmz olan dinamik olarak yaplandrabilmemiz.
So here what I'll do is all actually add an argument to this person function which named props.
Dolaysyla burada yapacam, aslnda sahne adn veren bu kiinin ilevine bir argman eklemeniz.
You can choose any name you want but the concept I'm using here is called prop's react automatically
stediiniz herhangi bir ismi seebilirsiniz, ancak burada kullandm konunun ad prop'un tepkisidir.
gives me an argument in that function I turned into a component with this syntax down here with the
Bu ilev bana otomatik olarak bir argman verir. Bu szdizimi ile burada
person J is X code and Propp simply contains all the attributes I add to my own component.
J kodlu X kodu olan bir bileene girdim ve Propp yalnzca tm ieriyor. kendi bileenime eklediim nitelikler.
So I could add name Max and age.
Bylece Max ve ya isimlerini ekleyebilirim.
Let's say twenty eight like this.
Bunun gibi yirmi sekiz diyelim.
If I do this now we can output this in our prison component.
Eer imdi yaparsam, bunu hapishane bileende yazabiliriz.
We just need to dynamically accessed this prop's element.
Dinamik olarak bu pervanenin esine erimeliyiz.
This prompts argument we output dynamic content and react with Cauley Brace's opening closing and only
Bu, dinamik ierii ktmz argman ister ve Cauley Brace'nin kapan kapanyla ve sadece bir iftle tepki
one pair.
verir.
No double curly braces only one pair of curly braces.
Hibir ift kvrck parantezi yalnzca bir ift kvrml parantez ierir.
And then we reach out to props and then Daut name to get this name attribute their past and prop's age
pervane yan pervanenin yandan itibaren geerli olan o ya kartmak iin atfetmek iin sahne uzantlarna
to output that age propertied past the prop's age and now we're using the properties the attributes
ve daha sonra Daut ismine uzanrz ve imdi, kendi bileene gemekte olduumuz nitelikleri kullanyor
we're passing to our own component and that's pretty cool because now if we repeat it does react darm
ve olduka serin nk imdi tekrar edersek Darm, P2 iin burada bir arama ilevi grr.
render a call here for P2.
Ve sonra bu adn gemii ve
So make sure to exchange isn't the second query selector.
Bu nedenle, ikinci sorgu seici deil alverii yaptnzdan emin olun.
We can pass different props to death component like Manue and 20:9 and now both components used the
Manuel ve Yeaya 20: 9 gibi farkl bileenleri lm bileenine geebiliriz ve imdi her iki bileen de grebildiiniz
same base as you can see.
kadaryla ayn taban kullanyordu.
They use the same function which is turned into a component by react but really taking advantage of
Reaksiyonla bir bileene dnen ancak bileen konseptinden gerekten faydalanan ayn
the component concept because we only wrote the HMO code once and now we can reuse it over and over
ilevi kullanyorlar nk sadece HMO kodunu bir kez yazdk ve imdi tekrar tekrar
again.
kullanabiliriz.
And I bet you can see the potential of this in very big applications.
Bahse girerim bunun potansiyelini ok byk uygulamalarda grebilirsiniz.
You can compose the entire application of reusable pieces and this component isn't even using any logic.
Tekrar kullanlabilir paralarn tm uygulamalarn oluturabilirsiniz ve bu bileen bile herhangi bir mantk kullanmyor.
It doesn't listen to clicks or stuff like that in apps such as the app we build in this course.
Bu derste oluturduumuz uygulama gibi uygulamalardaki tklamalar veya benzeri eyleri dinlemez.
We will of course do that.
Elbette bunu yaparz.
We will append our own logic to our components and then we have small reusable maintainable and easy
Kendi mantmz bileenlerimize ekleyeceiz ve daha sonra artc uygulamalar oluturmak iin her yerde
to manage pieces with their own logic contained in them which we can use anywhere to build amazing applications.
kullanabileceimiz kendi mantna sahip, yeniden kullanlabilir, bakm kolay ve kolay ynetilebilir paralara sahibiz.
That's the idea behind react and that is why it's so great and why does component concept is so great.
Tepki arkasndaki fikir bu ve bu yzden harika ve bileen kavram neden bu kadar harika deil ki?
Now let me do one more thing though.
imdi bir ey daha yapaym.
Right now I'm calling react on rendered twice.
u anda iki kez ilenmi olarak tepki veriyorum.
There's nothing wrong with that but actually we can also do this a bit differently.
Bunun yanl bir yan yok, aslnda biz de bunu biraz farkl yapabiliriz.
We couldn't have one if you're in the HMO part which has an idea of app or root.
Uygulama veya kk fikri olan HMO blmndeyseniz, bir tane bulamadk.
Doesn't matter any idea of your choice.
Seiminin fikri nemli deil.
Now get rid of the secondary act on render call and I will add a variable here.
imdi render arsnda ikinci hareketten kurtulun ve burada bir deiken ekleyelim.
This variable all name app but this name is also up to you.
Bu deiken, tm ad uygulamas ancak bu ad da size kalm.
But this very opposite will hold some j as X code.
Ancak bu tam tersi baz j kodunu X kodu olarak alacaktr.
I am just wrapping this in parentheses so that I can write this code over multiple lines.
Bu kodu birden ok satra yazabilmem iin parantez iine atyorum.
Now here what I can do is I can now output my person component as I did before we have to wrap it with
bir dalla tamamlamamz olsa da, GSX, yalnzca bir kk eye sahip olma gereksinimine sahip olduundan bitiik elere izin verilmemektedir.
a dip though because GSX has the requirement of only having one root element so adjacent elements are
imdi burada yapabileceim ey, benim kii bileenimi daha nce yapm olduum
not allowed.
gibi ktrabilmemin
I will also talk about this in of course though there are ways around this limitation.
Bu kstlamann etrafnda yollar olsa da, tabii ki bunun hakknda da konuacam.
So now I added a two person component usages to my app variable here and now is simply mount the app
imdi, iki deikenli bir bileen kullanmn benim uygulama deikenime ekledim ve imdi,
variable in the place of this element with the ID app which I select by adjusting my query selector.
sorgu seicisini ayarlayarak setiim kimlik uygulamas ile bu enin yerine uygulama deikeni baladm.
And now you see I get the two elements now next to each other.
Ve imdi grdn gibi, u anda birbirinin yanndaki iki elementi alyorum.
Because now they're rendered in the same hook in the same element.
nk artk ayn elementte ayn engeldir.
So to say in the same depth and this method of only having one hook one react on render a call and then
i ie gemi bileenlerle orada bir st ar oluturan bu yntem, tekrar eyleme uygulamalar oluturmak iin ok daha popler bir yol.
creating a up there with nested components is far more popular way of creating re-act apps.
Demek ki ayn derinlikte ve bu yntemi sadece bir ar oluturmada tepki veren ve
It is the way I will use in this course and in the next lecture I will talk about this.
Bu derste kullanacam yol budur ve sonraki konferansta bunun hakknda konuacam.
As the alternative with multiple react on render recalls.
oaltc tepki zerinde alternatif olduu gibi geri arr.
But be aware this is the way you will see far more often with this approach.
Ancak bunun, bu yaklamla ok daha sk greceiniz ekilde olduunu unutmayn.
You create so-called single page applications.
Szde tek sayfa uygulamalar oluturursunuz.
Now this is our first re-act app.
imdi, bu bizim ilk yeniden uygulama.
Now let's dive deeper into reactor.
imdi de reaktre doru daha derin dal yapalm.
Let's continue with the Chloris and really get started with re-act.
Chloris ile devam edelim ve gerekten yeniden davranmaya balayalm.